Finding Aid for National Organization for Women, Michigan Conference Records, 1969-1996
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
National Organization for Women, Michigan Conference Records
1969-1996
National Organization for Women. Michigan Conference.
85326 Bj 2
Records of various officers of the Michigan Conference of the National Organization for Women collected by one-time state presidents Margot Duley-Morrow and Alicia Perez-Banuet. Presidential files of Duley-Morrow, Nan Frost-Welmers, Shirley Monson, Lynn Hierholzer, Gloria Woods, and Alicia Perez-Banuet; files of state chapter developer Rhonda Drinan, and Macomb County chapter president Doris Little; contain correspondence, newsletters, clippings, mass mailings, agendas and minutes, photographs, and other materials concerning the formal and personal aspects of this feminist organization. Topics covered include the Equal Rights Amendment, the Project for Equal Education Rights, Women's Assembly III, and other issues pertaining to women's rights.
19 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records were donated primarily by Dr. Margot Duley-Morrow (Donor No. 7069 ) and Alicia Perez-Banuet (Donor No. 8608 ).
The record group is open to research.
The National Organization for Women was founded in 1966. The Michigan Chapter (later Conference) of NOW was convened in December 1969 by Patricia Hill Burnett in Detroit. By the middle of 1971 local chapters had been established in Big Rapids and Lansing. The first annual state convention was held in June 1972. A year later, Michigan NOW could boast of 17 local chapters and more than 1000 members. By 1983, the state organization had grown to 28 chapters and 6500 members (a loss of 1000 members from its August 1982 peak).
The formal structure of the state conference may be easily gleaned from the bylaws included in the collection. The bylaws of several local chapters (the structures of which usually closely resemble that of the state organization) are also represented. Briefly, the conference is directed by six elected officers, who form the Executive Committee. These executives are responsible to and form part of the State Coordinating Council (SCC), which meets three to five times a year. Ultimate power rests with the state membership, as represented at the annual state convention. The convention elects the state officers and sets broad policy agendas.
The central focus of attention for Michigan NOW (as for every other state chapter) from 1972 to 1982 was the proposed Equal Rights Amendment (ERA). The focus for Michigan NOW changed in the middle to late 80's as the state became involved in a heated and controversial battle over providing Medicaid funding for abortion. The Conference also played a key role in the battle for sex equity in Michigan public schools. The Conference has task forces on Lesbian Rights, Reproductive Rights, Economic Justice, Employment, Violence Against Women, and Homemakers' Rights, in addition to those on Education and the ERA, which give an indication of the organization's special concerns. In addition, local chapters are encouraged to mobilize for action on issues or events of local concern.
Michigan NOW attempts to implement its priorities by working within the political process. The Michigan NOW PAC (Political Action Committee) permits the Conference to lend financial as well as volunteer assistance to candidates it has endorsed. Michigan NOW's Legislative Vice-President is charged with mobilizing the state membership in support of or in opposition to bills at the state and national level judged important to the goals of the organization (these include not only "women's legislation," but also a broad spectrum of civil rights, military, foreign policy, and economic bills). The Conference also employs a professional lobbyist at the statehouse.
Some of the women who have been active as president in the Michigan Conference include (with dates of their presidency): Carol King, 1979; Barbara Miyata, 1980; Margot Duley Morrow, 1981-1983; Monica Smiley, 1983-1984; Barbara Hayes-Hamilton, 1984-1986; Marian McCracken, 1986-1988; Madeline Hansen, 1988-1990; Patty O'Donnell, 1990-1991; Lynn Hierholzer, 1991-1993; Gloria Woods, 1993-1995; Alicia Perez-Banuet, 1997-1998.
Margot Duley-Morrow served as president of Michigan NOW for two terms, 1981-1983. Prior to that she was the state ERA Task Force Chair (1979-1981), and Ann Arbor-Washtenaw County chapter ERA Task Force Chair. She joined the Ann Arbor chapter in 1975. Professor Duley-Morrow taught Women's Studies courses at the University of Michigan from 1975 through 1984; she also directed the Pilot Program (1975-1979) at the University, among other duties. She left Michigan in 1984 to become director of Women's Studies at Ohio's Denison University.
Summary Contents List
Margot Duley-Morrow, 1973-1984 (June-August 1984 accessions; boxes 1-9) Personal (box 1) Correspondence (with notes of telephone conversations, and memoranda (box 1) Michigan NOW (boxes 1-2) Michigan NOW Coalitions (boxes 3-4) Clippings (boxes 4-5) Ephemera (box 5) Nan Frost Welmers, President, 1977-1979 (box 5) Rhonda Drinan, Chapter Developer, 1977-1979 (boxes 5-6) ERA Task Force Chair (Judy Skog, 1978-1979; Karen Rice, 1977-1978) (Box 6) Shirely Monson, President, 1976-1977 (box 6) Local Chapter Files, 1969-1979 (box 6) Doris Little, Macomb County Now, 1980-1982 (box 7) Virginia Harris, Oakland County NOW, 1973-1977 (box 8) NOW Newsletters, 1972-1984 (boxes 8-9)
Alicia Perez-Banuet, 1972-1984 (1997 accession; boxes 9-10) Administrative (box 9) Legislation (boxes 9-10) Task Forces / Coalitions (box 10) Chapters (box 10)
Alicia Perez-Banuet, 1972-1992 (2001 accession, boxes 11-14) Topical File (boxes 11-13) Correspondence (box 13) Chapter Newsletters (box 13) Macomb County Now (box 13) Administrative Files (box 14) Officer Files (box 14)
Alicia Perez-Banuet, 1976-1996 (2004 accession; boxes 15-19) Governance (box 15) Administration (boxes 15-16) Lynn Hierholzer, president, 1990-1993 (boxes 16-17) Gloria Woods, president, 1987-1996 (boxes 17-18) Michigan NOW PAC, 1979-1994 (boxes 18-19) Legislative Committee, 1976-1994 (box 19)
The Michigan NOW record group includes administrative records, files of individual presidents, newsletters from local chapters, records of the Michigan NOW PAC (Political Action Committee), and topical files of subjects of interests to the Michigan Conference such as the ERA, educational equity, and abortion rights.
The organization of the collection is rather artificial, both because the documents were in extremely poor order upon their accession and because there is only the broadest unity to the collection's components. The records have been grouped under the name of the individual most responsible either for their creation or for their accumulation and preservation. There were two individuals primarily responsible for these records coming to the Bentley Library. They were Margot Duley-Morrow (two-term president, 1981-1983) who donated records in 1984 and Alicia Perez-Banuet (president, 1997-1998) who donated materials in three major accessions.
Subjects:
Equal Rights Amendments--United States.; Feminism.; Macomb County (Mich.); Michigan--Politics and government--1961-1970.; Michigan--Politics and government--1971-1980.; Michigan--Politics and government--1981-1990.; Michigan--Politics and government--1991-2000.; Michigan--Politics and government--1951-; Michigan Project on Equal Education Rights.; National Organization for Women. Michigan Conference.; National Organization for Women. Macomb County (Mich.) Chapter.; Political action committees--Michigan.; Social reformers--Michigan.; United States--Politics and government--1969-1974.; United States--Politics and government--1974-1977.; United States--Politics and government--1981-1989.; United States--Politics and government--1977-1981.; Women social reformers--Michigan.; Women--Michigan--Societies and clubs.; Michigan Women's Assembly.; Women's rights--Michigan.; Women in politics--Michigan.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Demonstrations.; Denmark.; Detroit (Mich.); Equal Rights Amendments--United States.; Feminism.; Feminists.; Kennedy Square (Detroit, Mich.); National Organization for Women.; National Organization for Women. Michigan Conference.; Slogans.; Women.; Women--Organizations.; Women's rights.
Contributors:
Drinan, Rhonda.; Duley, Margot I.; Frost-Welmers, Nan.; Harris, Virginia.; Hierholzer, Lynn.; Little, Doris.; Perez-Banuet, Alicia.; Woods, Gloria.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Margot Duley-Morrow, 1973-1984
  The Margot Duley-Morrow accession (1973-1984; boxes 1-9) is comprised of fourteen series: Personal, Correspondence, Michigan NOW, Michigan NOW Coalitions, Clippings, Ephemera, Nan Frost Welmers files, Rhonda Drinan Files, ERA Task Force Chair, Shirley Monson files, Local Chapter files, Doris Little files, Virginia Harris files, and NOW newsletters.
  - Personal
    Of particular interest in the Personal series (1974-1983) is the folder entitled "Pedagogical Issues re: ERA." It contains an interesting exposition of Duley-Morrow's opinions about the legitimacy of the opposition to ERA and about the limits of the "equal time" doctrine in the college classroom. In the same series are three interns' reports on no-fault (divisible) divorce, funding of domestic violence programs in Washtenaw County, and independent practices for dental hygienists.
    - Biographical (Box 1)
    - Early Feminist Activities
      - Ohio ERA Campaign, 1973 (Box 1)
      - Ann Arbor-Washtenaw County NOW, 1978-1979
        - Officers, Agendas, Treasurers Reports, etc. (Box 1)
        - ERA (Box 1)
        - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
    - University of Michigan
      - Commission for Women (Minutes, etc.), 1977-1978 (Box 1)
      - Women's Studies
        - Pedagogical Issues re ERA, 1979 (Box 1)
        - Interns' Projects, 1982-1983 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1979-1984
    Virtually all of the material in the Correspondence series (1979-1984) relates to Duley-Morrow's activities in Michigan NOW, first as ERA Task Force Chair and then as president. The topics of the correspondence run the gamut from requests for Duley-Morrow's participation in workshops and conferences to local chapter business, from policy discussions to more personal discussions of feminism. Duley-Morrow's correspondents include NOW officers at the local, state, regional, and national level, public officials, officers of other feminist, civil rights, and special-interest organizations, and representatives of the news media. Most of the correspondence are letters received, but some copies of letters sent are included as well. Included here as well are Duley-Morrow's notes of telephone conversations, which are quite legible, though at time cryptic. All in all, this series well-illustrates the varied duties and activities of a NOW state president, the broad affiliations of Michigan NOW in its pursuit of its goals, the personalities and relationships which vivify the organization: that is, both the formal and personal aspects of feminist activism are illuminated.
    - 1979-1980 (scattered) (Box 1)
    - 1981 (Box 1)
    - 1982, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - 1983 (Box 1)
    - 1984 (scattered) (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, Undated (Box 1)
    - Notes, Undated (Box 1)
  - Michigan NOW
    The Michigan NOW series (1976-1984) includes a variety of records. The officers meeting minutes, the state conventions materials, and the State Coordinating Council (SCC) materials contain information regarding the establishment and implementation of policy. However, there is not as much substance in these folders as there could be. Convention and meeting agendas and minutes are very scattered (especially for the state conventions). However, the ephemera from the conventions is in itself informative, and includes proposed resolutions, and announcements of workshops and other events. In addition, the 1980 convention material includes Duley-Morrow's ERA Task Force report notes and notes regarding the balloting for state officers. The 1983 convention is most completely documented, and includes Duley-Morrow's script for directing the proceedings. Scattered through the convention and SCC material are annotations and notes made by Duley-Morrow. Also included in the SCC folders are scattered reports from other state officers.
    The bulk of the NOW PAC documents are meeting handouts and Duley-Morrow's notes. But there are, too, bylaws, scattered minutes, some candidate questionnaires and voting records, mailings, fund-raisers and notes on endorsements. In general, the documentation of Michigan NOW's political activities is disappointingly scattered. The Education Task Force files are, however, supplemented by the more extensive Education subseries of the Michigan NOW Coalitions series.
    The communications subseries is especially noteworthy for two folders: the speeches, etc. of Duley-Morrow and the Hotline. In the former is a ringing one and a half page undated summary of Michigan NOW's recent accomplishments and activities, set against the Conference's limited resources. The Hotline is a series of one-page mailings from the state president to chapter presidents, announcing upcoming events, calling attention to special issues and urging calls and letters to public officials or the news media, asking for short-term volunteer help, announcing changes in agendas or personnel, and the like. The Topical File subseries is composed largely of secondary material on the issues listed.
    - General
      - Bylaws (Box 1)
      - Officers
        - Lists (Box 1)
        - Meetings
          - 1982-1983 (scattered) (Box 1)
          - June 1983 (Box 1)
          - Notes, Undated (Box 1)
      - Membership (Box 1)
      - Budgets (Box 1)
      - Dues and Miscellaneous Financial Information (Box 1)
      - Resolutions (Box 1)
      - Local Chapters
        - Administrative Miscellaneous (Box 1)
        - Ephemera (Box 1)
    - State Conferences
      - , Midland (from Rhonda Drinan files), June 1976 (Box 1)
      - , Ann Arbor, June 1977 (Box 1)
      - , Battle Creek (from Rhonda Drinan files), June 1978 (Box 1)
      - , Woodhaven, June 1979 (Box 1)
      - , (Chapter Development), March 1980 (Box 1)
      - , East Lansing, June 1980 (Box 1)
      - , Kalamazoo, June 1981 (Box 1)
      - , (Chapter Development), November 1981 (Box 1)
      - , Warren, June 1982
        - General (Box 1)
        - Plenary II (Box 1)
      - Livonia, June 1983
        - Preparations (Box 1)
        - General Information (Box 1)
        - Manual for Chapter Leaders (Box 1)
        - Minutes, Resolutions, Reports, Bylaws (Box 1)
        - Election (Box 1)
        - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
      - , Mid, June 1984 (Box 1)
    - State Coordinating Council (SCC)
      - Minutes, 1979-1984 (scattered) (Box 2)
      - Meetings, 1980-1983; 9 folders (Box 2)
    - NOW PAC
      - Bylaws (Box 2)
      - Minutes (scattered) (Box 2)
      - Meetings
        - July 1981, September 1981 (Box 2)
        - May 1982 (Box 2)
        - February 1984 (Box 2)
        - March 1984 (Box 2)
      - Notes and Miscellaneous
        - November 1979-December 1981 (scattered) (Box 2)
        - June-December 1982 (Box 2)
        - March-December 1983 (Box 2)
        - Undated (Box 2)
      - Legislators
        - Lists by Local NOW Chapters (Box 2)
        - Voting Records in State Legislature (Box 2)
        - NOW Endorsements (Box 2)
        - Miscellaneous Information
          - Purcell vs O'Reilly, Congressional Race, 1980 (Box 2)
          - Blanchard/ Griffiths, Gubernatorial Campaign, 1982 (Box 2)
          - Powers, University of Michigan Regents Campaign, 1982 (Box 2)
          - Reigle, U.S. Senate Campaign, 1982 (Box 2)
          - Sterling Heights State Senate Race (Venek vs. Wilson), 1982 (Box 2)
          - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
        - Campaign Literature (Box 2)
      - Mailings (Box 2)
      - Fund-raisers (Box 2)
    - Lobbying
      - List of Legislative Priorities, 1983 (Box 2)
      - Legislative Reports/Updates from Michigan NOW's Legislative Vice-President, 1979-1983 (scattered) (Box 2)
      - Specific Legislation
        - Eliot-Larson Civil Rights Act Legislation (Box 2)
        - Abortion (Box 2)
        - Job Partnership Training Act (Box 2)
        - Friend of the Court Reform (Box 2)
        - Set-aside Program for Women and Minority Business Owners (Box 2)
      - Miscellaneous Legislation
        - Drafts, 1981 (Box 2)
        - Michigan (Box 2)
        - National (Box 2)
    - Task Forces and Committees
      - Education Task Force (Patricia Klein, Chair), 1980-1982
        - Correspondence (primarily re MHSAA lawsuit), October 1979-April 1982 (Box 2)
        - Secondary Material on Women in High School Athletics in Michigan (Box 2)
        - Sex Equity in Public Schools, Miscellaneous (Box 2)
      - Lesbian Rights Task Force (Box 2)
      - Miscellaneous Task Forces (Box 2)
      - Fundraising Committee (Box 2)
    - Communications
      - Speeches, Reports, etc. by Duley-Morrow (Box 2)
      - Mailings over Duley-Morrow's Signature (Box 2)
      - Press Releases (Box 2)
      - Hotline, June 1979-April 1983; undated (Box 2)
    - Special Workshops: Defeating the Right Wing, January 1981 (Box 2)
    - Topical File
      - Gay Rights
        - Proposition 13, Seattle, 1978 (Box 2)
        - Proposition 6, California, 1978 (Box 2)
        - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
      - Insurance Rates, see Bias in (Box 2)
      - Lee, Rex, Nomination, 1981 (Box 2)
      - Military Issues and Feminism (Box 2)
      - Poverty, Women In (Box 2)
      - South African Divestment (Box 2)
      - Surrogate Parenting (Box 2)
      - Waitresses and Tax on Tips (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Michigan Now Coalitions
    The Michigan NOW Coalitions series highlights some of the social and political coalitions of which Michigan NOW is an important part. Of the five subseries, the first three--Education, ERA, and Women's Assembly III--are by far the most substantive and interesting. (Additional records relating to such coalitions will be found in the Michigan NOW, 1976-1979 subgroup and the Alicia Perez-Banuet subgroup).
    In the area of education, Michigan NOW made its most impressive contribution as a leader of the Michigan Project on Equal Education Rights (PEER). The Project's most significant effort was a suit filed against the Michigan High School Athletic Association (MHSAA) to equalize funding and access for women in high school sports (c. 1979-1983). Memos, documents, and correspondence concerning the suit, and drafts of the formal complaint make up the most important portion of the Education subseries, though other PEER material--including documents pertaining to other PEER athletics lawsuits--are also included.
    The ERA subseries combines activities of Michigan NOW and those of coalitions including Michigan NOW; most often there was no clear dividing line. The Mailings to Michigan NOW Officers folder contains memos on strategy and updates on events from the "Conference ERA Task Force Chair. The Campaign Kits folder contains two examples of nuts and bolts instructions for activists in raising funds, recruiting volunteers, and coordinating events. The two most important groups of documents in the subseries are the Notebooks and the ERAmerica material. The notebooks are presumably those of the task force chair, and include a rich hodgepodge of sources: cartoons, clippings, position papers, flyers, activists' primers, ERA Alerts, and much more. The opponents of ERA are documented in the notebooks, too, as are rebuttals to the main arguments of those opponents. The notebooks represent Michigan NOW's ERA campaigning in microcosm. ERAmerica was the nationwide organization bringing together and coordinating the diverse groups dedicated to passing the amendment. The material here relates to the Michigan branch, and contains five years of newsletters announcing events, warning of trouble, and disseminating information. Other ERAmerica material is scattered throughout the subgroup.
    Women's Assembly III began in 1982 as a two-day convention of representatives of 28 women's groups in Michigan, meeting "to develop a feminist platform with the purpose of supporting and working toward the goals of power for all women and women in all places of power: (from the Assembly's "Preface"). The Assembly, in response to the success of the original convention, did not dissolve, but formed a permanent network to pursue its goals, and in 1983 became a co-sponsor of the International Women's Year (IWY) National Women's Conference. The Women's Assembly III subseries is dense with substantive material, outlining its principles and structure, documenting its platform, and illustrating its shift from two-day conference to permanent network. The Assembly is especially important because it represents a rather broad feminist consensus, and hence may serve to help define the parameters of the movement in Michigan.
    - Education
      - Michigan Project on Equal Education rights (PEER)
        - Michigan PEER Perspective newsletter) (incomplete), October 1979-November, 1983 (Box 3)
        - Correspondence and Mailings (Box 3)
        - Reports, Goals, Brochures, etc. (Box 3)
        - Advisory Board Membership (Box 3)
        - Conference, October, 1981 (Box 3)
        - MHSAA Lawsuit
          - Memos, Documents, Correspondence, 1979-1983 (Box 3)
          - Drafts of Formal Complaint (Box 3)
      - Title IX, Miscellaneous
        - University of Michigan sports, Including Lawsuit, 1979; 1982 (Box 3)
        - Ann Arbor Schools (Box 3)
        - Dated Mailings and Correspondence (Box 3)
        - Miscellaneous, Undated (Box 3)
        - Budgets and Donors (Box 3)
        - Ford Foundation Grant (Box 3)
        - National PEER Perspective (scattered) (Box 3)
        - Miscellaneous (including scattered meeting minutes) (Box 3)
      - Michigan Education Association (MEA) Women's Caucus
        - The Activist (newsletter), May 1981-April 1983 (scattered) (Box 3)
        - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
      - Coalition for Non-Sexist Education (Box 3)
    - ERA
      - Lists of Michigan NOW Activists, 1979-1982; undated (Box 3)
      - Mailings to "Michigan NOW Officers, Chapter Presidents, and ERA Chairs,", 1979-1982 (Box 3)
      - Campaign Kits: from National NOW and Wisconsin NOW (Box 3)
      - Michigan ERA Information Notebook, 1976-1979; 3 volumes (Box 3)
      - Notebook, 1977-1978 (Box 3)
      - Notebook, 1978-1979 (Box 3)
      - Campaign Notes (Box 3)
      - Campus Campaign (University of Michigan) (Box 3)
      - Alerts, (scattered) (Box 3)
      - Speeches and Reports
        - Duley-Morrow (Box 3)
        - Others (Box 4)
      - Affiliated Groups
        - Michigan ERAmerica
          - Coalition Update (newsletter) (incomplete), 1978-1983 (Box 4)
          - Minutes, Budgets, Miscellaneous (scattered) (Box 4)
        - Michigan Labor Organizations (Box 4)
        - Others (Box 4)
      - Events
        - Michigan Walkathons, 1977; 1978 (Box 4)
        - Rally, Washington, D.C., June, 1978 (Box 4)
        - Call to Action Conference, Detroit, February, 1980 (Box 4)
        - Rally, Detroit, July, 1980 (Box 4)
        - A New Day Beyond ERA, Detroit, June, 1982 (Box 4)
      - Campaign in Other States
        - Illinois (Box 4)
        - Florida (Box 4)
        - Idaho (Box 4)
        - Missouri and Indiana (Box 4)
      - Miscellaneous
        - Mailings (Box 4)
        - Flyers (Box 4)
        - Etcetera (Box 4)
    - Women's Assembly III
      - Operating Principles and Structure, 1982; 1983 (Box 4)
      - The Assembly, June, 1982
        - Platform (Box 4)
        - Conference Materials
          - Education (Box 4)
          - Other (Box 4)
        - Participant's Notebook (Duley-Morrow) (Box 4)